An interface is like a facade or an outline of some imaginary class.
الواجهة هي مثل مقدّمة أو مخطط لفئة متخيّلة.
Its sole purpose is to be inherited by some other class.
وظيفتها الوحيدة هي أن ترثها فئة أخرى.
It only defines what needs to be done,
هي تحدّد ما ينبغي القيام به فقط،
but not how to do it.
لكنها لا تحدد كيفية القيام به.
In other words, the interface would list the methods that need to be
بعبارة أخرى، تدرج الواجهة الأساليب التي يجب تضمينها
included in the class but no implementation code whatsoever.
في الفئة، لكن من دون كود تطبيقي بتاتاً.
The implementation of these methods are
وتقع مسؤولية تطبيق هذه الأساليب على الفئات التي تطبّق تلك الواجهة.
Once you implement that interface in a class,
بمجرد تطبيق تلك الواجهة في فئة ما،
you can then start instantiating objects as usual.
يصبح بالإمكان البدء بإنشاء مثيل للكائنات كالمعتاد.
The reason Java introduced interfaces is because of the multiple inheritance problem.
يعود سبب تقديم لغة Java للواجهات إلى مشكلة التوارث المتعدد.
A single class can be extended by multiple classes.
يمكن توسعة فئة واحد من خلال فئات متعددة.
But a child class is not allowed to extend more than one parent class.
لكن لا يُسمح لفئة فرعية بأن تكون امتداداً لأكثر من فئة رئيسية واحدة.
Interfaces, however, don't have that restriction,
أما الواجهات لا تواجه هذا الحصر،
which means that a single class can implement multiple interfaces allowing
ما يعني أن بإمكان فئة واحد تطبيق عدة واجهات،
for a more flexible design but without the ambiguity problem of the multiple inheritance.
ما يسمح بوجود تصميم أكثر مرونة لكن من دون وجود مشكلة الالتباس للوراثة المتعددة.
Let's have a look at an example.
لنتناول مثالاً على ذلك.
Imagine you're responsible of implementing a class called Caravan.
تخيّل أنك مسؤول عن تطبيق فئة تسمى Caravan.
We know that a caravan is half vehicle, half house.
نعلم أن الكارافان هو نصف سيارة ونصف منزل.
But if you had a class for a vehicle and a class for a house,
لكن إذا كان لديك فئة لسيارة وفئة لمنزل،
we know that you're not allowed to extend both classes at the same time.
نعلم أنه لا يُسمح لك بمدّ كلتا الفئتين في آن واحد.
A good solution would be to introduce interfaces.
حل جيد لهذه المشكلة هو استخدام الواجهات.
A good interface would be the movable interface, for example,
من الواجهات المناسبة واجهة اسمها Movable مثلاً،
which would define the methods that any class that moves should include,
وهي تعرف الأساليب التي يجب أن يتضمّنها أي فئة تتحرّك،
like the vehicle class, for example.
مثل فئة vehicle على سبيل المثال.
Another good interface would be called the habitable interface,
وهناك واجهة أخرى مناسبة وهي واجهة Habitable،
which would also define all the methods that are to be included for any habitable class.
وهي واجهة تعرّف كافة الأساليب التي ستتضمنها أي فئة يمكن السكن فيها.
Once we define those two interfaces,
بعد أن عرّفنا هاتين الواجهتين،
we could then implement both of them in the Caravan class at the same time.
يمكننا تطبيقهما معاً في الوقت ذاته ضمن فئة Caravan.
Let's have a look at the Java code for that.
لنلقِ نظرة على كيفية كتابة ذلك في كود Java.
Creating an interface in Java is very similar to creating a class.
إنشاء واجهة في لغة Java يشبه كثيراً إنشاء فئة.
Simply swap the keyword class with interface.
نستبدل فقط الكلمة الرئيسية class بالكلمة الرئيسية interface.
Inside the interface, as you can see,
أما داخل الواجهة، كما ترون،
we have listed the method signatures but without
قمنا بوضع أسطر تعريف الأسلوب لكن من دون أي كود تطبيقي،
the responsibility of the class that will be implementing that interface.
لأن هذا يقع على عاتق الفئة التي ستطبّق تلك الواجهة.
The same for the habitable interface,
والأمر نفسه مع واجهة habitable،
which in our case here only includes the canFit method.
وهي في هذه الحالة تتضمّن أسلوب canFit فقط.
Once we create both of those interfaces,
بعد أن أنشأنا كلتا الواجهتين،
we can then start implementing our Caravan class,
يمكننا البدء بتطبيق فئة Caravan،
which implements both the habitable and movable interfaces.
وهي تطبّق كلاً من الواجهتين Habitable وMovable.
Notice that I've used the keyword, implements,
لاحظوا أنني استخدمت الكلمة الرئيسية implements هنا
here compared to the keyword, extends.
مقارنة مع الكلمة الرئيسية extends عند الوراثة من الفئات.
implements is the keyword to use when inheriting from interfaces.
إن الكلمة الرئيسية implements هي التي تُستخدم عند الوراثة من الواجهات.
Once we implement those interfaces,
بعد أن طبّقنا هاتين الواجهتين،
we have to implement the code for
يتوجب علينا تطبيق الكود لكل أسلوب متضمَن في كلتا الواجهتين،
the move method which was included in the moveable interface
مثل أسلوب move الذي كان مُتضمناً في واجهة Movable،
and the canFit method which was included in the habitable interface.
وأسلوب canFit الذي كان مُتضمناً في واجهة Habitable.
If there's any method in any of
إذا كان هناك أي أسلوب في أي من هاتين الواجهتين لم يتم تطبيقه في فئة Caravan،
that will show a compilation error.
سينجم عن ذلك خطأ في التحويل البرمجي.
Notice that inheriting interfaces hasn't really saved us
لاحظوا أن وراثة الواجهات لم تجنبنا
from rewriting any code like we've done before with extended classes.
من إعادة كتابة أي كود كما فعلنا سابقاً مع الفئات الموسّعة.
That's because interfaces isn't there to help
وهذا لأن الواجهات ليست موجودة لمساعدتنا
us reduce code as much as enforce a good design.
في تقليص حجم الكود بقدر ما أنها تفرض تصميماً جيداً.
Creating interfaces forces any class that will
يفرض إنشاء الواجهات على أي فئة ستستخدمها أن تستخدم عدداً محدداً من الأساليب.
This means that later on,
هذا يعني أنه لاحقاً،
if you have a look at any class that implements
إذا ألقيتم نظرة على أي فئة
a certain interface without looking at the code of that class,
تطبّق واجهة معينة من دون النظر إلى كود تلك الفئة،
you can guarantee that it will include all these methods that are in that interface.
فيمكنك أن تجزموا بأنها ستتضمّن كافة تلك الأساليب الموجودة في تلك الواجهة.
So, to summarize everything so far,
لنلخّص كل ما سبق،
we know that interfaces define what a class should do,
نعلم أن الواجهات تحدد ما يجب على الفئة فعله،
but not how to do it.
لكن ليس كيفية القيام به.
We've seen that creating an interface is very similar to creating a class,
رأينا أن إنشاء واجهة يشبه كثيراً إنشاء فئة،
and we know that the interface's sole purpose
ونعلم أن الوظيفة الوحيدة للواجهة
is to be implemented by one or more classes.
هي أن يتم تطبيقها من قبل فئة واحد أو أكثر.
That is, you're not allowed to create
أي أنه لا يسمح لكم بإنشاء مثيل أو كائن من الواجهة مباشرة.
You have to first implement it through a class,
عليك أولاً تطبيقها من خلال فئة ما،
and then you can create objects from that.
ثم يمكنكم إنشاء كائنات من ذلك.
And we've seen that it's not about reducing code or partition.
وقد رأينا أن لا علاقة له بتقليص تكرار الكود.
It's more about enforcing a good design.
بل يتعلق أكثر بفرض تصميم جيد.